Finding Aid for the Tulancingo (Hildago, Mexico) Manuscript Collection, 1567-1882 LSC.2073
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Pre-1837 manuscripts, ca. 1567-1837; 2.5 boxes
  - [Prohibition against playing games], 1792 October 25; 1 bifolium: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 2, Folder 29)
    Broadside containing an edict (bando) from Don Juan José Ossorio Moctezuma, of the Real Audiencia: He forbade residents from playing hopscotch and ball games in public spaces. He stated that transgressors would be fined and punished.
  - [Miscellaneous coversheets], 1792 and 1793; 2 leaves and 1 bifolium: paper; various sizes (Box 2, Folder 30)
    Coversheets which have been separated from larger packets of documents.
  - [Town reports], 1793 July 16 - August 4; 4 leaves and 1 bifolium: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 2, Folder 31)
    Reports from the constituencies of the jurisdiction of Tulancingo. Each head town (cabecera) sent in a list of their own dependent pueblos, ranchos and haciendas.
  - [Felipe Badillo's opposition to his son's marriage], 1794 January 17 - 21; 1 leaf and 1 bifolium: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 2, Folder 32)
    Felipe Badillo presented a petition protesting the marriage of his son Ygnacio Badillo with Anastacia Beliz. Badillo, the father, considered Beliz to be inferior to his family and was vehemently against their matrimony. He tried punishment to stop his son.
  - [Report on the local post office], 1794 February 12; 1 bifolium: paper; 30 x 21 cm. (Box 2, Folder 33)
    Report by Juan M. Arellanos, administrator of the local post office, to subdelegate Don Francisco Lardizaval. Arellanos described the inner workings of the organization, giving the names of the workers there and details on their various mail routes.
  - [Report from Don Juan Ygnacio Assiayn [Asiain], Administrator of Tobacco], 1794 April 30; 1 bifolium: paper; 30 x 21 cm. (Box 2, Folder 34)
    Report details the number of sheets of paper (pliegos), gunpowder, card decks and materials for cigar-making used in 1773.
  - [Report on bovine consumption], 1794 May 10; 1 leaf: paper; 30 x 21 cm. (Box 2, Folder 35)
    Report on the number of cows consumed in Tulancingo and its dependencies in 1793. The total was 705.
  - [List of reports], ca. 1794; 1 leaf: paper; 30 x 20 cm. (Box 2, Folder 36)
    List of reports stating which administrators would report on what items. Referenced the reports of Asiain and Arellanos (cf. box 2, f.27 & f.26 respectively).
  - [Statement on the destruction of tobacco plants], 1795 November 17; 2 bifolia: paper; 30 x 21 cm. (Box 2, Folder 37)
    Documents relating to the destruction of tobacco plants grown in the mountains of Tulancingo and Huauchinango, ordered by the Real Hacienda by inspector Don Domingo Sanz. Includes a lengthy list naming indigenous men caught with sown tobacco fields.
  - [Indigenous leaders of Atotonilco vs. Don Miguel Larralde], 1795 November 26 - 1796 January 25; 56 leaves: paper; 32 x 22 cm. (Box 2, Folder 38)
    Indigenous leaders of Atotonilco denounced the local justice administrator (encargado de la administracion de justicia), Don Miguel Larralde, for his unjust oppression. They were represented by Don Francisco Rubin de Celis. Documents reveal accusations.
  - [Complaint of Doña Maria Gertrudis Ruis], 1796; 1 leaf and 1 bifolium: paper; 31 x 21 cm. (Box 2, Folder 39)
    Doña Maria Gertrudis Ruis, widow of Don Antonio Guerrero, initiated a complaint against José Maria Marques. Marques had been trying to marry Ruis's daughter, Maria Manuela Guerrero. Ruis felt that they were not equal.
  - [Deposition of Anselmo Rodriguez Baldo], 1796 March 16; 6 leaves: paper; 30 x 22 cm. (Box 2, Folder 40)
    Anselmo Rodriguez Baldo presented testimony against Don Antonio Duran and Duran's mother Doña Antonia Perez. Rodriguez was a cleric and owner of Hacienda de Totuapa el Grande. He protested Duran's attempt to create a new mill. Document is a copy, signed.
  - [Agustin Felipe de la Cruz and José Antonio de la Cruz vs. Hacienda de San Pedro de las Baquerias], 1796 April 29 - May 21; 5 leaves: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 2, Folder 41)
    Action involving Agustin Felipe de la Cruz and José Antonio de la Cruz, indigenous, who worked on the Hacienda de San Pedro de las Baquerias [San Pedro Vaquerías] since childhood. They felt that they had been denied their full salary and were mistreated.
  - [Copies of letters], 1796 May 21; 2 bifolia: paper; 30 x 21 cm. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Transcriptions of about eleven letters. Includes information on the search for fugitive Frenchmen, the Mill of Santiago, local area tribute payments, the contraband of pulque and other prohibited drinks, and others.
  - [Report to the Viceroy on unemployment], 1796 August 2 - 1797 January 21; 2 leaves and 2 bifolia: paper; various sizes (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Viceroy Branciforte requested a report on the residents of the jurisdiction, to determine unemployed (vago)indigenous, mulattos or blacks in the area. Documents include responses from local leaders, and a letter of reply to him from Jose Ximenes del Rio.
  - [Letter about a donation from Tulancingo], 1796 November 11; 1 leaf: paper; 30 x 21 cm. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Rought draft letter to Viceroy Brancifort indicating residents of the jurisdiction of Tulancinco had made a monetary donation of $1673 (plus 100 more from the author) pesos.
  - [Request for church documents from the Real Tribunal], 1796 December 19; 1 leaf: paper; 30 x 21 cm. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Copy of a letter by José Ximenez del Rio to the Viceroy, asking for the return of documents (expediente). They were sent to the Real Tribunal and concerned the local church in Tulancingo.
  - [Documents concerning the formation of local military companies], ca. 1796 - 1797; 9 leaves: paper; various sizes (Box 3, Folder 5)
    In accordance with the Viceroy's orders, three militia companies (compañias sueltas de milicias) were formed. They each consisted of 120 local men and were made up of a mixed ethnic group (Spaniards, Mestizos, and Castizos).
  - [Regulations on selling food in the market], ca. 1797; 1 leaf: paper; 31 x 21 cm. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Various vendors have been caught selling fruits, seeds, chiles, etc. at the market at deflated prices (regatonería). Four provisions were enacted to regulate their business.
  - [Letters from L. M. de Perea], 1797 January 1 - 1798 January 3; 1 leaf: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Copies of two letters by L. M. de Perea (?). One discusses the harvesting of cotton and chile which was sold in the market. The other asked Don Cadena to deliver a certification to the judge of the general court.
  - Sup[eri]or or[de]n p[ar]a q[u]e los Ec[lesiasti]cos no exersan la Abogacia, 1797 April 5 - May 10; 4 leaves: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Title translates as: "Superior order so that ecclesiastics do not practice law." A letter from the Viceroy Branciforte mandated that clerics were not to practice law. Don Manuel de Perea, lawyer of the Real Audiencia, sent the notice out locally.
  - [Military inscription records], 1797 June 22 and 1798 September 8; 2 leaves: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Two separate inscription records for Mathias Gomez and José Bisente Morgado. The documents describe their physical features in detail and bound them to a twelve-year service contract with the military.
  - [Letters concerning enlisters], 1797 September 30; 1 bifolium: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Copies of three letters concerning military recruits: Gregorio Antonio Perez, Joseph Miguel Lopez (of Atotonilco), and Ysidro Lascano (of Tantoyuca?).
  - [Miscellaneous correspondence], 1797 October 3 and December 16; 1 leaf: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Two letters: One from Miguel Nazianzono Lopez to Don José Ximenes del Rio, and another (impartial copy) from Don Pedro Garibay.
  - [Don José Ximenes del Rio's report on the women's jail], 1797 October 25; 1 leaf: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 3, Folder 12)
    The subdelegate of Tulancingo, Don José Ximenes del Rio, decided to close the women's jail and relocate them to a special house. The document reveals what he considered to be the problems associated with these women.
  - [Copies of unsigned letters], 1797 November 4; 1 leaf: paper; 30 x 21 cm. (Box 3, Folder 13)
    Copies of four letters by an unsigned author. They concern: an acknowledgement of the alliance between Spain and France, a verification that no foreigners had entered the area, recognition of orders to capture Don Juan Ramon y Duran.
  - Ynformacion recivida apedimento de la parte del Cura del Pueblo de Tututepeque Contra Juan Tolentino y socios sobre varios exesos, 1797 November 18 - December 29; 66 leaves: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 3, Folder 14)
    Title translates as "Information received at the request of the priest of Tutotepec against Juan Tolentino and his associates for their various excesses." Juan Tolentino, his son Nicolas Tolentino, and his brother Juan de San Agustin (all Spanish- speaking).
  - [Brigada Gertrudis Santos vs. Gregoria the widow], ca. 1798; 1 bifolium: paper; 30 x 22 cm. (Box 3, Folder 15)
    Brigada Gertrudis Santos complained to local authorities about Gregoria, the widow, who was having an illicit affair with Santos's husband, Antonio de San Juan (indigenous). The document reveals problems that existed between these two women.
  - [Documents concerning the Otomí of Huehuetla and the Tepehua of Tenango], 1798 January 24 - April 12; 2 leaves and 3 bifolia: paper; various sizes (Box 3, Folder 16)
    Correspondence documenting the conflict between the Otomí of Huehuetla and the Tepehua of Tenango. The Otomí had two requests: the right to elect a governor and a priest to teach them Christian dogma.
  - [Copies of miscellaneous letters], 1798 February 10 - 24; 1 bifolium: paper; 30 x 21 cm. (Box 3, Folder 17)
    Copies of nine letters, concerning various topics.
  - [Receipt of compendium], 1798 April 22; 1 leaf: paper; 13 x 21 cm. (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Copy of a brief letter, which mentions having received the compendium on the method of mulberry tree raising.
  - Diligencias practicadas en virtud del Escrito que las principia sobre el Tumulto formado en el Pueblo de Tututepeque entre los Naturales del mismo Pueblo como adentro se expresa, 1798 May 27 - June 1; 25 leaves: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 3, Folder 19)
    Title translates as "Proceedings concerning the tumult in Tutotepec among the Indigenous who live there, as expressed within." The Tolentinos and others were accused of instigating a riot (cf. box 3, f.1). A drunk man was accused of cursing at a priest.
  - [Letter about the coming of the Viceroy], 1798 June 16; 1 leaf: paper; 21 x 15 cm. (Box 3, Folder 20)
    Copy of an unsigned letter. The author received notice that the Viceroy would stay in the town so he could learn about the army troops which were there because of the war with Great Britain.
  - [Letter to Don Jose Ximenez del Rio from Calado], 1798 October 16; 1 leaf: paper; 30 x 21 cm. (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - [Letter to Don Gaspar Martin], 1798 November 3; 1 bifolium: paper; 21 x 16 cm. (Box 3, Folder 22)
    Unsigned letter to vicar Don Gaspar Martin. The author won $2000 pesos in the lottery. He informed vicar Martin of how the money would be used and related other news.
  - [Accusations of witchcraft], 1799 August 13 - 24; 7 leaves and 1 bifolium: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 3, Folder 23)
    Josefa Manuela, an indigenous woman from Tenango who appeared to have been a traditional healer, was accused of witchcraft by Josefa Estefania and Mariana Pascuala. The priest Don Juan Anselmo Rodriguez Pizarro placed Josefa Manuela in jail for three months.
  - [Casiano Martinez vs. Maria Josefa Perez], 1799 August 19 - September 24; 13 leaves: paper; 32 x 22 cm. (Box 3, Folder 24)
    Dispute between Casiano Martinez and Maria Josefa Perez. Casiano Martinez claims defendant Perez has a well-venerated painting (lienzo) of San Antonio del Jacalito which belonged to his family. He demanded its return and other items.
  - Expediente promovido p[o]r Pioquinto Campozano sobre q[u]e se verifique el matrimonio que tiene tratado con D[oñ]a Dolores Araujo, 1799 September 11 - 17; 9 leaves: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 3, Folder 25)
    Title translates as "Proceedings instigated by Pioquinto Campozano concerning the verification of his engagement to Doña Dolores Araujo." Pioquinto Campozano [Canposano] was engaged to Doña Maria Dolores Araujo, but he could not marry her.
  - [Charges of prostitution], 1807 March 12 - April 6; 4 leaves: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 3, Folder 26)
    Juan Agaton Luvian was accused of prostituting María Meriotegui (his cousin), on the Temascalillos ranch. File includes testimony of Luvian, the family's problems, and the reason for what happened.
  - [Indigenous petition from Santa Ana Hueytlalpan], 1807 September 10; 4 leaves: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 3, Folder 27)
    Indigenous governors of Santa Ana Hueytlalpan petitioned to denounce the exploitation they suffered from the head-town (cabecera), particularly from Don Marcelo Santuario and Don Mateo Milpas. They listed their tribute obligations.
  - [Mine claim of Anastacio Antonio Rios], 1807 December 29 - 1808 January 2; 3 leaves: paper; 31 x 21 cm. (Box 3, Folder 28)
    Anastacio Antonio Rios found a metal deposit in the mountains and issued a formal claim to the Pachuca authorities. The authorities ask the subdelegate (subdelegado) of Tulancingo to place notices (rotulones) in public places for three consecutive Sundays.
  - [Luis Coronado vs. José Mariano Asiain], 1810 February 26 - March 3; 4 leaves: paper; 31 x 21 cm. (Box 3, Folder 29)
    Provision from the Real Audiencia. Don José Mariano Asiain of Atotonilco was in a dispute with Don Luis Coronado over a purchase price (of bulls?). With signatures of the oidores (without the official seal).
  - Cabildo hecho en Huasca para alarmarlo en defensa de la Justa causa contra los Ynsurgentes, 1811 January 7 - 9; 5 leaves: paper; 32 x 22 cm. (Box 3, Folder 30)
    Title translates as "Meeting held in Huasca in preparation of the just cause of defense against the insurgents." Documents related to the defense of Huasca de Ocampo from the insurgents of the War for Independence.
  - [Plans for the defense of Tulancingo against insurgents], 1811 January 11 - 12; 1 bifolium: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 3, Folder 31)
    Document noting the progress and reaction to the independence movement, and the promotion of defense plans for the area from insurgents. Signed by Don Jose Sandoval.
  - [Complaint against Ignacio Adalid, tavern owner], 1811 May 4 - July 10; 2 leaves: paper; 31 x 21 cm. (Box 3, Folder 32)
    Complaint brought against pulque tavern owner in Acatlán named Don Ignacio Adalid where people "commit many excesses and speak with liberty in favor of the insurrection."
  - [Inventory of the estate of Don Pedro Escorra], 1817 February 19 - May 10; 4 leaves: paper; 32 x 22 cm. (Box 3, Folder 33)
    Estate inventory compiled by Juan Martinez de Oropesa at the request of Doña Maria Guadalupe Hernandez, widow of Don Pedro Escorra. Document lists the lands that Escorra owned, their values, his debts and bequeaths a statue of Christ [El Señor Crucificad]
  - [Don Ysidro and Don Nicolas Jusue vs. Jose Francisco Perez], 1818 September 11 - 1828 May 22; 31 leaves: paper; 32 x 22 cm. (Box 3, Folder 34)
    Don Ysidro and Don Nicolas Jusue, brothers in Spain, sought to collect a debt from Don Jose Francisco Perez of Atotonilco, el Grande. The documents illustrate the long litigation process, which spanned the colonial, imperial, and independent eras.
  - [Criminal case against Crisanto de la Cruz and Maria Jacinta], 1820 May 26 - June 2; 1 bifolium: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 3, Folder 35)
    Provision from the Real Audiencia. Crisanto de la Cruz and his wife Maria Jacinta were accused of murdering José Eugenio, husband of Ana Rosalia. Contains oofficial seal and signatures of the oidores.
  - [Law in preparation for the celebration of the Virgin Mary], 1820 December 7; 1 leaf: paper; 31 x 21 cm. (Box 3, Folder 36)
    The mayor Don Jose Francisco Perez declared it illegal for people to consume pulque or snacks in the vicinity of the altars of Mary, as to avoid drunkenness and trivialities. Violators were to be fined 2 pesos.
  - [Public announcement], 1821 April 15; 1 leaf: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 3, Folder 37)
    Broadside announcement prohibiting more than three men on horseback to be out after nine at night.
  - [Letter from Francisco Abendaño], 1822 July 17; 1 leaf: paper; 31 x 22 cm. (Box 3, Folder 38)
    Letter from Francisco Abendaño to Don Pedro de Torres y Miranda in Tulancingo concerning cattle ranching and taking the herd through various places (like Chalma and Calnali), and the difficulties he faced.
  - [Military draft], 1826 May 28 - 29; 1 bifolium: paper; 32 x 22 cm. (Box 3, Folder 39)
    Local officials conducted a military draft of sixty men from the community. Documents describes how the draft was carried out and lists the names of all the men who were inscribed.
  - [Legal defense argument for Jacinto Ramirez], 1828 May 12; 1 leaf and 1 bifolium: paper; 32 x 22 cm. (Box 3, Folder 40)
    Jacinto Ramirez was jailed for military desertion. His lawyer Jose Zeferino de Melo presented a lengthy argument to set Ramirez free which revealed his ideas about liberty and civil rights in the fledgling nation.
  - Sobre cobrar á los renuentes el prestamo forsoso de que habla la ley 30 de Junio de 1832, 1832 August 17 - 1833 April 14; 22 leaves: paper; various sizes (Box 3, Folder 41)
    Title translates as "Concerning forced payment on delinquent loans, which the law of June 30, 1832 allows for." The government of Tulancingo was applying the law of June 30, 1832, which allowed for forced payment collection on delinquent loans.
  - Esped[ien]te promovido por parte del Jusgado de Testam[en]tos, Capellanias y Obras pias de este Arzobispado, en solicitud de que se le entre en la posesion hereditaria de los bienes que quedaron, por fallecimiento de D[oñ]a Rita Ramires, 1837 September 6 - 1838 April 20; 17 leaves: paper; 32 x 23 cm. (Box 3, Folder 42)
    Title translates as "Proceedings instigated, by the Juzgado de Testamentos, Capellanías y Obras Pías of this archbishopric, to gain hereditary possession of the estate which remained after the death of Doña Rita Ramírez."
  - [Request by Don Agustin Paredes Arrillaga], 1837 December 4; 1 leaf: paper; 32 x 22 cm. (Box 3, Folder 43)
    Don Agustin Paredes Arrillaga, representing Don Agustin Suares de Peredo, requested the mortgage books (libros de hipoteca) for Hacienda de la Bolsa (?) to be registered.
- Post-1852 manuscripts, 1854-1877; 5 boxes
  Series consists of civil and criminal litigation documents.
  - Año de 1854; ...de oficios, 1854-1855; 90 leaves (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Documents pertaining to the estates of Doña Joséfa de Sobrales, Doña Mariana de Yslas, Don Manuel Pérez y Morales and others.
  - Decreto del Gob[ier]no G[ene]ral disponiendo el modo de...tirar la deuda interior, 1857, 8 leaves (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Unsigned draft outlining various issues and proposals concerning the interior debt.
  - Acta del juicio verbal promovido sobre pesos por el Ciudadano Manuel Fernández contra D[oñ]a Jesús Hurtado, 1862-1879; 28 leaves (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Civil suit involving a financial dispute between Manuel Fernández and Doña Jesús Hurtado. Folder includes an authorization of attorney signed by Doña Jesús Hurtado allowing Don José María LÓpez to represent her in the lawsuit.
  - [Settlement of the estate of Bernabé Madariaga], 1863-1867; 112 leaves (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Documents pertaining to the estate of Bernabé Madariaga.
  - [Mixto de Civil y Criminal], 1863 - 1868; 7 leaves (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Criminal case involving Don Dimas LÓpez who was accused by Don Miguel Lastire of robbery at a ranch in Ayotla.
  - Peticiones que el que suscribe articula a Don Nestor GarzÓn, 1863-1870; 53 leaves (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Petitions and correspondence regarding a legal matter involving Don Nestor GarzÓn, a Spaniard.
  - El Lic. D. José M[arí]a Carvajal como apoderado de D[on]a Ana Ramos Amador contra D[on] Antonio Amador sobre administraciÓn de bienes y rendiciÓn de cuentas, 1864-1869; 23 leaves (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Probate documents for the estate of Don Juan Amador. Doña Ana Ramos Amador was named executor of her husband's estate and guardian for their child, María Rafaela. Issues arose between Ana Ramos Amador and Antonio Amador concerning the distribution of as[sets].
  - Juicio de inventarios por memorias simples de la Testam[iento] a de Don Longinos Escorcia, 1864-1867; 17 leaves (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Probate documents for the estate of Don Longinos Escorcia. File includes a judgment concerning the estate inventory and a petition by Rafael Cortés, guardian for decedent's minor children Erlinda, Manuel, Julian, Dolores, and Adolfo Escorcia.
  - Autos del intestado de Doña Margarita Vera, 1866-1870; 27 leaves (Box 4, Folder 9)
    Legal documents pertaining to the intestacy of Doña Margarita Vera.
  - [Antonio Martínez vs. heirs of Bernabé Madariaga], 1866-1870; 51 leaves (Box 4, Folder 10)
    Legal documents that include an accounting of the estate's assets and debts.
  - Interdicto retinendi - promovido por lo veino del rancho de la Concepcion [Buenavista] contra Don Ygnacio Gonzales dueno del rancho del Ventorrillo, 1867-1871; 93 leaves (Box 4, Folder 11)
    Legal documents and petitions relating to a dispute between Rafael Martinez and Don Yganico Gonzales, owner of the Ventorrillo ranch.
  - Judicio ordinario sobre pesos El C. Manuel Palacios contra el de igual clase Antonio Guzman, 1867-1868; 25 leaves (Box 4, Folder 12)
    Civil suit over money entitled Manuel Palacios versus Antonio Guzman. Documents include an accounting of debts owed by Don Antonio Guzman.
  - Promovido por Don Ygnacio Moreno Ordoñez en representacion de Doña María de los Angeles y de Don Simon Porfirio Valenzuela, deduciendo derecho a los bienes del intestado de Don Agustin Valenzuela, 1867-1869; 51 leaves (Box 4, Folder 13)
    Probate documents for the intestacy of Don Agustin Valenzuela include an estate inventory. Documents reflect that Doña María de los Angeles bore a child by Don Agustin Valenzuela, who was legally married to Doña Joséfa Ochoa.
  - Memoria testamentaría de la S[eno]ra D[on]a ... Micaela Montez en tres fojas útiles del sello tercero del vienio de mil ochocientos sesenta y ocho y mil ochocientos sesenta y nueve Febrero ocho de mil ochocientos sesenta y ocho, 1868-1872; 9 leaves (Box 4, Folder 14)
    Will and testament of Doña Micaela Montez.
  - Autos del intestado de Darío Cubas, 1868-1869; 8 leaves (Box 4, Folder 15)
    Legal documents pertaining to the intestacy of Dario Cubas.
  - Ejecutivo sobre pesos promovido por D[on] Pedro María Soto, contra D[on] Ygnacio Urquijo, 1868; 8 leaves (Box 4, Folder 16)
    Civil suit over money initiated by Don Pedro María Soto against Don Ygnacio Urquijo.
  - Juicio civil ordinario sobre pesos, promovido por D[on] José Victor Garzon contra D[on] Manuel Rodriguez Madariaga, 1868; 31 leaves (Box 4, Folder 17)
    Civil suit over money entitled Don José Victor Garzon versus Don Manuel Rodriguez Madariaga.
  - Acta del juicio verbal promovido por el Ciudadano Manuel Fellez contra el de igual clase Antonio Guzman, sobre pesos, 1869; 14 leaves (Box 4, Folder 18)
    Verbal judgment in furtherance of resident Manuel Fellez's claim against Antonio Guzmán, an individual of the same class, regarding money.
  - Juicio ejecutivo sobre pesos, promovido p[o]r el [Señor] Jesus Escorcia conta el de igual clase Antonio Pérez Arroyo, 1869; 19 leaves (Box 4, Folder 19)
    Executive judgment in a financial dispute in the entitled action Señor Jesus Escorcia versus Antonio Pérez Arroyo.